<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="text">
<body><div>
    <pb facs="#f009"/>
<ab>
			<div>
				<p>
				Enforce your wyll su?yng as for to learen <lb/>
				Acanns? your with coning for that ys sevre?<lb/>
				yf fortenne chanc &amp; poverte? apere<lb/>
				he that ys coning ys lyke to recover<lb/>
				<figure>
					<figDesc>
						<desc>Line separating the verse above from the notes below</desc>
					</figDesc>
				</figure>
				a pownde ys wryte thys ƚi:i:<lb/>
				halfe a pownde thys: ƚi:d: or thys: ƚi:β:<lb/>
				an unce ys thys: ℥:i: or thys ℥:i:<lb/>
				halfe an unce thys: ℥:d: or this ℥:β:<lb/>
				a drame is thys: Ʒ:i:<lb/>
				halfe a drame this: Ʒ:d: or this :Ʒ:β:<lb/>
				a quart : qrt:<lb/>
				a scrypul ys thys: Ȝ:i:<lb/>
				halfe a scrypul: Ȝ:d: or thys :Ȝ:β:<lb/>
				a handeful thys: m:i:<lb/>
				halfe a handeful: m:d: or m:β:<lb/>
				of every <add>one</add> yche myche this: an: or thys: ana<lb/>
				a grayne ys thys: gra: or grana:<lb/>
				<persName>Henry Dyngley</persName>:ano xpo:<date>1554</date>: et ano philippi et marie primo et secundo <date>vicessimo secundo die marcii</date><lb/>
				xii: unce make a pownde: and viij: drames make one unce and .iij. scripuls one drame: and xx: barly cornis ys a scripul<lb/>
				</p>
			</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f010"/>
<ab>

			<div>
				<head>
					<title>Divers receits.</title>
				</head>
			<head>
				<title>De urinis</title>
			</head>
				<head>
					<title>De signis zodiaci &amp;amp;c</title>
				</head>
			</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f011"/>
<ab>

		<div>
		<figure>
			<figDesc>
					<desc>Black-and-white drawing of King Henry VI carrying a sword with a banderole captioning the figure.</desc>
			</figDesc>
			</figure>
		<p>Henricus vi Rex anglie</p>
		</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f012"/>
<ab>
		<div>
				<desc>Three lines of cancelled notes. Illegible.</desc>
			</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f013"/>
<ab>
	<div>
		<desc>Blank flyleaf</desc>
			</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f014"/>
<ab>
		<div>
				<head>
					<title>for the ache of <rs>disease in the raynes</rs> of the bakke</title>
				</head>
				<p>Take a <measure>quarter of yard </measure> of redde scarlett &amp; stycche therto the woll of a blakke shepe thatt growyth apon the brest and then take pouder of [?]aunders &amp; 
				strew over the sayd woll &amp; also pouder of lycoras and after that don to over spryngyll the same with oyle of oylyff and that plastur shall restore nature. 
			And ease the pacient of his disease so it be layed to his raynes &amp; <measure>every wyke</measure> the same plastre to be renewed with same pouder &amp; oyle. 
			And so to use it till he be hoole &amp;c.</p>
			</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f015"/>
<ab>
			<div>
				<figure>
					<figDesc>Ex libris stamp of Trinity College Cambridge Library</figDesc>
				</figure>
				<p>Collegium S.S. et individuae Trinitatis in Academia <placeName>Cantabrigiensi</placeName></p>
			</div>
</ab>

<pb facs="#f016"/>
<ab>
			<div>
				<head>
					<handShift/>
				<title>of all maner of Infyrmytes</title>
 					<handShift/>
 				</head>
 				<p>Here begynneth a tretys of al manere of infirmitees of mannys body. 
 				bothe withinne as touchyng to phisyke and withoute as touching to surgerie 
 				from the croune of the heed to the sool of the foot. And the remedies therwith 
 				if god wol. And furst we wol at heer of the hed how it shulde be norisshede &amp; kepte &amp;c.</p>
 			</div>
				<div>
				<head>
					<title>For to make heer to growe.</title>
				</head>
				<p>Take withien leves and sethe hem in oyle and hony and anoynte the heede 
				therwith. and it shal make the heer to growe and waxe. 
				<title>Another.</title> Take beer &amp; drie hem in a furneys or in a panne
				 and make therof a pouder. and sethe it in hony and anoynt the pacient therwith and it schal 
				 make the heer to growe. <title>Another.</title> forto make heer to growe after scalles. 
				 There is an oynement that is cleped <term>unguentum <persName>aristotilis</persName></term>. 
				 thus it must be made. Take the sewet of a dere either fresshe shepys talu and 
				 pich that is fletyng. oyle olyf and gret salt. of iche of these <measure>iii. unces</measure> 
				 or <measure>half a quartron</measure> of white waxe <measure>half an unce</measure>. 
				 than first take the sewt. or </p>
  </div>
  </ab>
  </div>
  </body>
      </text>